Finding Aid for John A. Jacquez Papers 1937-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
John A. Jacquez Papers 1937-1999, 1962-1998
Jacquez, John A. (John Alfred), 1922-
6 linear feet
John Jacquez was a professor in the University of Michigan's Medical School and School of Public Health and was active in his field of biostatistics. The collection contains correspondence and materials relating to his teaching, research and conference activities.
02145 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
This collection was donated by Marianne Jacquez (donor number 9016 ) in September 2000.
The collection is open for research.
John A. Jacquez has been associated with the University of Michigan since 1962 as a professor of physiology and biostatistics at both the Medical School and the School of Public Health. Born in France on June 26, 1922, he and his family immigrated to New York in 1929. Jacquez earned his undergraduate degree (1943) and MD. (1947) from Cornell University, after which he had a productive tenure at the Sloan-Kettering Institute for Cancer Research in New York. He taught at the University of Michigan from 1962 until his retirement in 1990. Even in the 1990s he continued to teach with emeritus status and to be active with his research on the spread of HIV and an AIDS vaccine. Jacquez died October 16, 1999 at the age of 77.
The papers of John A. Jacquez document his career both as a teacher and a researcher from the 1960s to the 1990s. The collection is arranged into five series, Personal/Biographical, Correspondence, Teaching Material, Research Material, and Conference Material.
Subjects:
Jacquez, John A. (John Alfred), 1922-; AIDS (Disease)--Research--United States.; AIDS (Disease)--Study and teaching--Michigan.; Biometry.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Medical School.; University of Michigan. School of Public Health.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Jacquez, John A. (John Alfred), 1922-
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Personal/Biographical
  The Personal/Biographical (0.25 linear feet) series contains information about his education, military service, and sabbatical activities (including a scrapbook of letters, articles and photographs of his time spent at the Fogarty Center in Maryland). Also contained here are photographs of Jacquez.
  - Photographs, 1987 and late, 1990s (Box 1)
  - Education
    - Junior high school/High school 1937-1939 (Box 1)
    - Cornell University: College of Arts & Sciences 1940-1943 (Box 1)
    - Cornell University: Medical College 1944-1947 (Box 1)
    - Columbia University 1946-1953 (Box 1)
  - Army career 1946-1958, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - IBM/National Institutes of Health 1959-1962 (Box 1)
    (includes photographs)
  - Fogarty International Center 1982-1984 (Box 1)
  - Fogarty International Center scrapbook 1982-1984, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence (1.25 linear feet) series is comprised of professional material for the most part, although there are personal letters scattered throughout. This series is divided into two subseries, "By name" and "By date." By name files include correspondence with research partners and colleagues, students, and academic journals, for which he often reviewed submissions. Note that although Jacquez filed correspondence with graduate students and post-doctoral students together, these categories are not entirely inclusive. Researchers should check the alphabetical name listing or under the specific category (graduate or post-doctoral) when looking for a particular student name. There are a small number of files in the By date subseries all of which include letters, drafts and notes relating to his peer reviews for academic journals.
  - By name
    - AIDS Conference Departmental Paper 1988 (Box 1)
    - American Journal of Physiology 1998 (Box 1)
    - American Physiological Society 1997 (Box 1)
    - Norman Bailey 1993-1999 (Box 1)
    - Richard Bellman 1958-1983, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - John J. Biesele 1959-1963, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Ewart Carson 1996-1997 (Box 1)
    - Gilbert Chauvet 1979-1997, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Horace Davenport 1962-1989, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Sara Debanne 1996-1997 (Box 1)
    - Klaus Dietz 1990-1995 (Box 1)
    - Elsevier Science Publishing Co., Inc. 1993-1994 (Box 1)
    - David Foster 1972-1999, 2 folders (Box 1)
      (includes photograph)
    - General 1984-1987 (Box 1)
    - Graduate students
      - Claude Cote 1976-1990 (Box 1)
      - Charles Hawkins 1969-1986 (Box 1)
      - John Koch 1982-1985 (Box 1)
      - Thomas Krenitsky 1962-1987 (Box 1)
      - Michael Shanahan 1986, 1989 (Box 1)
      - H.E. Skipper 1970 (Box 1)
      - Kent Stitzer 1972-1975 (Box 1)
      - Nelly Ullman 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - István Gyori 1993-1994 (Box 1)
    - Institute for Mathematics and Its Application (IMA) 1997-1999 (Box 1)
    - Journal of Biological Systems 1990-1993 (Box 1)
    - Edward H. Kaplan 1990 (Box 1)
    - Thomas Krejcie 1995-1999 (Box 1)
    - James Matis 1997-1998 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous 1956-1997 (Box 1)
    - National Cancer Institute 1999 (Box 1)
    - National Institutes of Health 1998 (Box 1)
    - Marija Norusis 1972-1981 (Box 1)
    - Philip O'Neill 1992 (Box 1)
    - Tim Perry 1994 (Box 1)
    - Robert Phair 1978-1987 (Box 2)
    - Physiology Department Centennial 1981-1982 (Box 2)
    - Post-doctoral students
      - Michael Bazin 1967-1973 (Box 2)
      - Earl Christensen 1964-1971 (Box 2)
      - Daniel Fife 1970-1979 (Box 2)
      - Donald Foster 1969-1997 (Box 2)
      - Warren Glaser 1967-1969 (Box 2)
      - Lynn Graves 1963-1971 (Box 2)
      - William Hirschfeld 1965-1970 (Box 2)
      - Robert Haas 1989 (Box 2)
      - Howard Kutchai 1966-1986 (Box 2)
      - Patricia Labine 1964-1972 (Box 2)
      - Gerald Portney 1965-1970 (Box 2)
      - Robert Serfling 1963-1971 (Box 2)
      - Roger Weinberg 1963-1965 (Box 2)
      - Jan West 1963-1976 (Box 2)
      - Leigh Whitlock 1963-1989 (Box 2)
    - Rand Corporation 1959-1960 (Box 2)
    - C.P. Rhoads 1957-1959 (Box 2)
    - Thomas Riggs 1999 (Box 2)
    - Michael Savageau 1992, 1997 (Box 2)
    - James Schafer 1966-1993 (Box 2)
    - Stanley Schultz 1973 (Box 2)
    - James Sherman 1959-1962 (Box 2)
    - Sloan-Kettering Institute for Cancer Research 1947-1962 (Box 2)
    - Arthur Vander 1970 (Box 2)
    - J. Wu 1991 (Box 2)
  - By date
    - 1993 (Box 2)
    - 1994-1999, 3 folders (Box 2)
- Teaching Material
  The Teaching Material (2 linear feet) series contains lecture notes as well as slides and overhead transparencies used for courses he taught at the University from 1967-1999. The bulk of this material dates 1967-1981, but Jacquez was granted emeritus status and continued to teach even after retiring.
  - Computing workshops 1962-1963, 1966-1968, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Physiology 540 1974-1977, 2 volumes (Box 2)
  - Physiology 540 1974-1977 (cont.), 2 volumes (Box 3)
  - Physiology 540 1979-1980, 2 volumes (Box 3)
  - Physiology 540 circa 1980, 8 folders (Box 3)
    (includes transparencies)
  - Physiology 618 1982-1997 (Box 4)
  - Epidemiology 602 1992 (Box 4)
  - Epidemiology 624 1999 (Box 4)
  - Irreversible thermodynamics (Box 4)
  - Facilitated diffusion theory (Box 4)
  - Respiration 1967-1979, 2 folders (Box 4)
- Research Material
  The majority of the Research Materials (1.5 linear feet) series consists of files relating to Jacquez' research activities. Files have been identified as well as possible and separated into two subseries, AIDS and Other. The AIDS subseries relates to research with colleagues James Koopman, Carl Simon and Ira Longini and includes data, notes, drafts of papers as well as published articles by Jacquez, and information about several computer programs used in data analysis. Other files contain information about various research topics. Some of these files may actually be related to Jacquez' AIDS research, but could not be identified as such.
  - AIDS Research
    - SAAM Institute 1998 (Box 4)
    - Resource Facility for Kinetic Analysis (RFKA) 1994-1995 (Box 4)
    - Identifiability (includes slides) (Box 4)
    - IDENT Consults 1989-1994, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - IDENT, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - MACS/CCS, 7 folders (Box 4)
    - HIV (Box 4)
    - HIV data (Box 4)
    - Simulations (Box 4)
    - Staging (Box 5)
    - Multiple partners 1993 (Box 5)
    - Dendritic cells/Macrophage (Box 5)
    - Vaccination, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Vaccination evaluation (Box 5)
    - R0, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Epidemic models 1998 (Box 5)
    - Marriage and epidemic models 1991 (Box 5)
    - Background, summaries 1997 (Box 5)
    - Randomization tests 1998-1999 (Box 5)
    - James Koopman (Box 5)
    - Journal of AIDS papers, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Other Research
    - Urinary tract infection (UTI) (Box 5)
    - Lab notebook 1985-1986 (Box 5)
    - Analysis of variance 1965-1968 (Box 5)
    - Kalman-Bucy filters 1999 (Box 5)
    - Linares (Box 5)
    - Chris Riolo (Box 5)
    - Early work 1945-1947 (Box 5)
    - Papers, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Homeostasis chapters, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Statistics text 1985-1986 (Box 5)
- Conference Material
  Jacquez attended many conferences and lectures in the U.S. and abroad from 1971-1996. He presented at almost all of them and, in some cases, organized them as well. The Conference Materials (1 linear foot) series contains correspondence, brochures, lecture notes and slides. Because the files are arranged chronologically, researchers can get a sense of how Jacquez' research interests may have changed throughout those years.
  - Miscellaneous 1971-1978, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Michigan State University lectures 1972 (Box 5)
  - Lyman Briggs College Senior Seminar in Mathematical Biology November 30, 1972 (Box 5)
  - AAAS Symposium on "Models for Transport in Biological Systems December 28, 1973 (Box 5)
    (includes photographs and slides)
  - Thomas Lumsden circa February 3, 1973 (Box 5)
    (includes slides)
  - IEEE International Symposium on Circuit Theory April 9, 1973 (Box 6)
  - University of Tennessee lectures November 29-30, 1973 (Box 6)
  - History of Physiology 1974-1987 (Box 6)
    (includes slides and negatives)
  - Miscellaneous 1976-1980 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous 1979-1989, 4 folders (Box 6)
  - International Conference on Nonlinear Phenomenon in Mathematical Sciences June 16-20, 1980 (Box 6)
  - Mathematical Association of America meeting August 18-20, 1980 (Box 6)
  - Mathematical Modeling in Biomedical Research January 23-25, 1984 (Box 6)
  - AIDS: Modeling & Analyzing HIV Transmission: The Effect of Contact Patterns May 2, 1990, 2 folders (Box 6)
    (includes slides and transparencies)
  - Workshop on Epidemic Spread: Stochastic Modelling & Data Analysis August 8-12, 1990 (Box 6)
  - Operations Res. Soc. meeting October 28-29, 1990 (Box 6)
  - Workshop: Mixing and Contact Patterns June 28-29, 1991 (Box 6)
  - Centre International de Recontres Mathematiques November 4-8, 1991 (Box 6)
    (includes photograph and transparencies)
  - Epidemiological Modeling Workshop December 2-4, 1991 (Box 6)
  - Integrative Approaches in Neurophysiology December 9-10, 1991 (Box 6)
  - 3rd International Conference on Mathematical Population Dynamics June 1-5, 1992 (Box 6)
  - Second Geoffrey J. Butler Memorial Conference on Differential Equations & Population Biology June 17-20, 1992 (Box 6)
  - Isaac Newton Institute January 3-9, 1993 (Box 6)
  - The role of primary infection in the opidemics of HIV infection in gay cohorts, 1994. (Box 6)
  - Association of University Anesthesiologists Satellite Symposium on Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics May 3-5, 1994 (Box 6)
  - Mathematical Modeling in Experimental Nutrition V May 8-11, 1994 (Box 6)
  - International Conference on Differential Equations and Applications to Biology and to Industry June 1-4, 1994 (Box 6)
  - Mathematical Models for Infectious Diseases November 27-December 3, 1994 (Box 6)
  - Conference on Dynamical Systems in Biology and Medicine July 17-20, 1996 (Box 6)